<articles>
<article id="0000017" published-at="2004-07-29" title="SAN FRANCISCO / Head of Juvenile Probation Department under fire / Gas leaks, criticism over reform progress may doom Tucker"><p>Chief juvenile probation officer <a href="/search/?action=search&amp;amp;channel=politics&amp;amp;inlineLink=1&amp;amp;searchindex=solr&amp;amp;query=%22Gwendolyn+Tucker%22" type="external">Gwendolyn Tucker</a>, in charge of the city department that incarcerates and attempts to rehabilitate thousands of children accused of committing crimes, is facing a flood of criticism from youth advocates, her staff and <a href="/search/?action=search&amp;amp;channel=politics&amp;amp;inlineLink=1&amp;amp;searchindex=solr&amp;amp;query=%22Juvenile+Probation+Commission%22" type="external">juvenile probation commission</a>ers who are considering whether to fire her.</p> 
<p>The Juvenile Probation Commission held an emergency meeting Monday that lasted long into the night and is reconvening again today to discuss Tucker's fate.</p> 
<p>Tucker, who was promoted from assistant chief last summer after then- chief <a href="/search/?action=search&amp;amp;channel=politics&amp;amp;inlineLink=1&amp;amp;searchindex=solr&amp;amp;query=%22Jesse+Williams%22" type="external">Jesse Williams</a> quit, has been accused of ignoring gas leaks and fire hazards at Log Cabin Ranch for boys, not working hard enough to send youths to community rehabilitation programs rather than the juvenile hall lockup, and clashing with her staff.</p> 
<p>Tucker has not publicly answered her accusers and referred all questions, including those about past or present gas leaks and other operational issues, to her private attorney, <a href="/search/?action=search&amp;amp;channel=politics&amp;amp;inlineLink=1&amp;amp;searchindex=solr&amp;amp;query=%22Gregg+Adam%22" type="external">Gregg Adam</a>. Adam said Tucker will meet behind closed doors with commissioners sometime during today's meeting.</p> 
<p>"She will respond to the commission," Adam said. "It's not appropriate for her to respond publicly."</p> 
<p>The possible shakeup at the <a href="/search/?action=search&amp;amp;channel=politics&amp;amp;inlineLink=1&amp;amp;searchindex=solr&amp;amp;query=%22Juvenile+Probation+Department%22" type="external">Juvenile Probation Department</a> is just one more controversy for a department that has struggled with what youth advocates say is one of the highest incarceration rates in the state. There have been two major reform efforts since 1996 to reduce the number of minors in lockup by sending low-risk offenders into community programs. But watchdogs have said both efforts have made little impact.</p> 
<p>"It takes dedicated, willful leadership, the kind of leadership we might have to find outside of San Francisco," said <a href="/search/?action=search&amp;amp;channel=politics&amp;amp;inlineLink=1&amp;amp;searchindex=solr&amp;amp;query=%22Andrea+Shorter%22" type="external">Andrea Shorter</a>, deputy executive director of the <a href="/search/?action=search&amp;amp;channel=politics&amp;amp;inlineLink=1&amp;amp;searchindex=solr&amp;amp;query=%22Center+on+Juvenile%22" type="external">Center on Juvenile</a> and Criminal Justice, a think tank and lobbying group that advocates rehabilitation programs rather than incarceration.</p> 
<p>About a year ago, the Juvenile Probation Department adopted a new intake questionnaire meant to help probation officers determine whether recently arrested children should be locked up while awaiting their court date or released to a community program. Kids are graded according to the severity of their alleged crime, history and flight risk.</p> 
<p><a href="/search/?action=search&amp;amp;channel=politics&amp;amp;inlineLink=1&amp;amp;searchindex=solr&amp;amp;query=%22Ntanya+Lee%22" type="external">Ntanya Lee</a> of Coleman Advocates for Children and Youth said 93 percent of arrested juveniles were incarcerated when the new intake procedure was adopted. A year later, she said, kids who are considered low risk are still being locked up because probation officers are ignoring the new system.</p> 
<p>Lee said Mayor <a href="" type="internal">Gavin Newsom</a> made a campaign promise to appoint a new chief, and she is still waiting. The mayor has been slowly replacing department heads since he took office seven months ago.</p> 
<p>The Juvenile Probation Commission might move ahead without him.</p> 
<p>At Monday's commission meeting, Lee joined other watchdogs and employees who testified about Tucker's job performance. Tucker's supporters included her director of special programs for youth, who declined to be interviewed later.</p> 
<p>Mercedes Hernandez-Bran, the department's human resources director, told the commission that since December she has tried to alert Tucker and her staff about gas leaks and fires in the kitchen and laundry room at Log Cabin Ranch, a residential program in La Honda. But Hernandez-Bran alleged that her warnings were pushed aside.</p> 
<p>Longtime cook <a href="/search/?action=search&amp;amp;channel=politics&amp;amp;inlineLink=1&amp;amp;searchindex=solr&amp;amp;query=%22Jeff+Hatton%22" type="external">Jeff Hatton</a>, who didn't attend the meeting, told The Chronicle that he always smells gas and that there was a leak last week that resulted in a small fire.</p> 
<p>La Honda volunteer fire Chief <a href="/search/?action=search&amp;amp;channel=politics&amp;amp;inlineLink=1&amp;amp;searchindex=solr&amp;amp;query=%22Larry+Whitney%22" type="external">Larry Whitney</a> said his crew has responded to about six calls from the ranch since November, and one incident included a gas leak in the administration building. He said that although there have been a few more calls than usual, none of the incidents was significant.</p> 
<p>Meanwhile, Tucker and her attorney are awaiting the commission's next move. Adam said he will argue that labor laws for peace officers afford her the right to appeal a dismissal, if that's what is coming.</p></article>
</articles>
